["Orange Colored Sky"
by Nat King Cole playing]
♪ I was walking along.
minding my business ♪
♪ When out of an orange colored sky ♪
♪ Flash. bam. alakazam ♪
♪ Wonderful you came by ♪
♪ I was humming a tune
Drinking in sunshine ♪
♪ When out of that orange colored view ♪
♪ Flash. bam. alakazam ♪
♪ I got a look at you... ♪
[applause]
[song continues playing]
♪ One look and I yelled timber... ♪
[newscaster over radio] Negotiations
were scheduled to continue today
As the White House had no comment
about the President's whereabouts.
[Mr. Handy] Ready to be
of service. madam.
[newscaster on TV] ...between America
and her adversaries
crumbled this morning
in Anchorage. Alaska.
The specter of nuclear war
facing this nation
For ten long years is final...
It's a party. Let's just focus
on the party. okay?
[indistinct chatter]
[song continues playing]
♪ Pretty green polka dot sky ♪
♪ Flash. bam... ♪
[girl] Look at that!
[cheering and applauding]
[man] Well done!
[indistinct shouting]
All right. birthday boy.
Let's get a photo of you
up here on Sugarfoot.
Why the hell is Cooper Howard
working kids' birthday parties?
-What else? Alimony.
-[chuckles softly]
What'd they say. Dad?
That I'm lucky to have
such a good helper like you.
All right. you ready?
-It's good.
-All right. good.
Here we go. bud. [grunts]
Hey. honey. Honey. get with Cooper.
Let's get a picture.
-Uh. you bet. Yeah. All right.
-[chuckling]
Oh. Coop. Coop. Coop. do your thumbs-up.
Yeah. given the state of everything.
I prefer not to. if that's all right.
Why not? It's what you're famous for.
-Drop it. Bob.
-Yeah.
We gotta...
we gotta get this rodeo on the road.
I can't thank you enough. Mr. Howard.
Pleasure's all mine. ma'am.
I hope your son had a lovely birthday.
-Perfect.
-Yeah.
Who's ready for cake?
-[children] Me!
-[Cooper] All right. You ready. Janey?
[children laughing and shouting]
[Cooper clicks tongue]
Come on. There you go.
-Pinko.
-Yep. He still took my money.
[all singing]
♪ Happy birthday. dear Roy ♪
♪ Happy birthday to you ♪
-[man whistles]
-[cheering]
[horns blowing]
Here's that Los Angeles sunshine
coming through.
Hal... I can't... I can't--
Sorry. I can't do the weather if I don't
know if there'll be a next week.
Only thinking happy thoughts today.
...the Nuka Cola bottle...
[announcer] Sugar Bombs presents Grognak the Barbarian
and the Ruby Ruins
[children laughing and cheering]
[man on TV] And. as I say
this is hi from the past!
[groaning] All right.
[man on TV] I'm sick of you.
[Cooper] Think that's everything.
[grunts]
Why wouldn't you do it?
The thumbs-up.
Oh. it's. uh
...
[smacks lips] It's grown-up stuff.
[smacks lips]
Back when I was in the Marines.
They taught us that if they ever
dropped a really big bomb.
They told us to hold up your thumb
just like this.
And if the cloud is smaller
than your thumb.
Then you run for the hills.
And if it's bigger than your thumb?
They told us not to bother running.
Do you think it's gonna happen?
I certainly hope not.
But us cowpokes.
we take it as it comes. right?
Can I have a slice. Dad?
Know what. let me see
if I can't rustle you up a piece.
[TV playing indistinctly]
[laughing]
-[door closes]
-[camera shutter clicking]
[distant whooshing]
[silence]
[Cooper] All right. one piece of cake
coming up for my favorite cowgirl.
-Is it your thumb or mine?
-[sighs]
That's smoke. Janey. It's just a fire.
[rumbling]
[muffled shouting]
-Let us in.
-No room.
-Bob...
-Back off!
Bob!
["Don't Let the Stars Get In Your Eyes"
by Perry Como playing]
My name is Lucy MacLean.
And I'm an active contributor
to the well-being of my community.
Repair skills.
I enjoy participating
in the Young Pipefitters' Association.
Which keeps me active. [chuckles]
Science skills.
Obviously. minor.
nothing compared to my dad's.
But I always relish a challenge.
Speech skills.
My primary passion
is teaching American history.
With a focus on ethics.
I also participate in Gymnastics Club.
Fencing team C.
Intermediate phys-ed.
And I dabble in riflery.
Though. I'm not very good.
[chuckles nervously]
In my personal time.
I enjoy taking walks
and watching movies with my dad.
Gardening. also with my dad.
And participating
in my family book club.
We're still trying
to get my brother on board.
He'll come around when he's ready.
My reproductive organs are intact.
my hygiene. well-maintained.
And yet. I have been unable
to find a suitable marriage partner.
At least one I'm not related to.
And we have rules about that
for a reason.
So. it is with sound mind and body
That I hereby submit
my application to the council
To participate in the triennial trade
with Vault 32.
[clicking]
[chiming]
[beeping]
Norman.
Feels a little tight.
Won't be for long.
On my wedding night. that dress got off
almost as fast as Burt did.
Huh.
[exhales] Oh. gosh.
After ten years of cousin stuff.
I'm definitely excited
for the real thing.
Oh. Lucy. I am just excited for us
to raise our kids together.
[Lucy chuckles softly]
[Lucy chuckles]
[projector whirring. flickering]
[chuckling] Dad.
-My little sugar bomb. Oh.
-[chuckling]
Oh.
Gosh. you look just like your mother.
Yeah. I wish she was here.
Me too.
Were you scared...
When you married Mom?
Me? [scoffs]
-Terrified.
-[both chuckle]
Well. I'd never stepped foot
outside Vault 31.
When did it go away?
The moment I met your mother.
[Rose] Lucy.
[indistinct]
Lucy.
From that moment on.
Vault 31 was a distant memory to me.
[Betty] Overseer. It's time.
[vault door whooshing]
[door opens]
Must be nerve-racking.
Your husband could be anybody.
I'm aware.
-As for his looks...
-Who knows?
Big butt. no butt.
But that's just a superficial concern.
-It's what's on the inside that counts.
-That's right.
And in that respect.
he could be a cannibal
Or just crammed full of tumors...
-Norman!
-[door opens]
Sorry. Dad.
[rumbling]
[Hank] Gatekeeper.
Chet?
Honestly... textbook tumbler jam.
It's gonna take some time to fix.
Probably best if we reschedule
with the 32s
-Until maintenance and I can...
-Chet.
What's going on?
[softly] Lucy. I love you.
We all know that. Chet.
Messing around with your cousin.
it's all well and good for kids.
But it's not a sustainable
long-term sexual practice. you know?
Yeah. I know.
[clicks]
[alarm buzzing]
[muffled rumbling]
Welcome. neighbors from Vault 32.
I am Hank MacLean. Overseer of Vault 33.
Lee Moldaver. Overseer of 32.
Thank you for your hospitality.
Oh. we were sorry to hear
of Overseer Jackson's passing
In your telegrams.
When blight hit our wheat.
we lost a lot of good people.
But this trade will help us
get back on our feet.
Yes. well. as arranged. we offer you
seed and parts for machinery.
In exchange. we offer you a breeder.
So...
[chuckles]
Who am I marrying? [chuckles nervously]
I'm Lucy.
Do you have a name?
Monty.
[whispering] Lucky.
["Who Do You Suppose"
by Connie Conway playing]
[applause]
♪ Who do you suppose I really love... ♪
[indistinct chatter]
So. what's your sperm count?
Uh...
Your Vault's doctor must check
every physical. no?
I mean. sperm is pretty important
in perpetuating America.
-[chuckling] So...
-[Stephanie] Stop.
[applause]
Good evening and welcome
to the proud denizens of Vault 32.
[applause]
We are bonded not just as neighbors.
But by a shared duty.
To keep the candle of civilization lit
While the rest of the world
has been cast into darkness.
Soon. if our measurements are correct.
Radiation levels on the surface
are dropping fast enough
That the next generation.
Lucy and Monty's children.
Will be able to recolonize.
-[laughs]
-[applause]
[whooping]
[man] Yeah!
[Hank] Yes
Now. after 200 years...
We don't know much
about what's up there.
Desperation. violence. lawlessness.
These survivors will need
to be shown a better way.
I'll admit. I'm sometimes afraid
That mean old world
will change us instead.
But then I look at my daughter...
Such a beautiful bride.
and her new husband...
And I am not afraid.
I feel hope.
To Lucy MacLean.
and to this marriage. and to hope.
[cheers and applause]
Let's dance. Ha-ha. Hit it.
["Some Enchanted Evening" playing]
♪ Who can explain it? ♪
♪ Who can tell you why? ♪
♪ Fools give you reasons ♪
♪ Wise men never try ♪
♪ Some enchanted evening ♪
♪ When you find your true love ♪
♪ When you feel her call you... ♪
Let's dance.
[song continues playing]
♪ Across a crowded room ♪
♪ Then fly to her side... ♪
["Start It Slow" playing]
♪ So. listen. my prince... ♪
[laughter]
[Lucy] You're the worst.
Show me to my new home?
[Lucy chuckles]
[Lucy] This is us.
[Lucy exhales. chuckles]
Ah. isn't it great?
Every big moment of our lives
is gonna happen right here.
Picture the Christmas mornings
around the tree.
We have everything
with the hand-me-downs.
An icebox. a blender.
They even gave us...
Huh.
Okey dokey.
["Keep That Coffee Hot" playing]
♪ Keep that coffee hot ♪
♪ Keep it hot... ♪
[Lucy chuckles]
♪ Be sure to make a lot ♪
♪ Make a lot ♪
♪ Your coffee hits the spot ♪
♪ It hits the spot ♪
♪ So keep that coffee hot ♪
♪ So keep it hots ♪
♪ I love your coffee pot ♪
♪ I love your pot ♪
♪ So keep that coffee hot... ♪
[moans]
[Monty moans]
[indistinct chatter]
[Monty exhales]
[exhales]
[chuckles]
[sighs]
[eerie music plays]
Hello?
[muffled booming in distance]
[grunts softly]
[faucet opening and closing]
[distant yelling]
-[woman screaming]
-[gunshots]
[static crackling]
[crackles rapidly]
You're from the surface.
Raiders.
[Lucy grunting]
[both grunting]
[yells]
-[groaning]
-[high-pitched ringing]
[breathing heavily]
[Lucy panting]
[Monty] Just so you know...
This was the best day of my life.
[grunts]
[yelps]
[Lucy grunting]
[grunts]
[slashes]
[yelps. grunts]
[knife piercing]
[Lucy gasps. panting]
[alarm blaring]
[yells]
[yelps]
[gurgles]
[groaning]
[panting]
[yelps]
[labored breathing]
-[grunts]
-[hisses]
[alarm continues blaring]
[door opening]
-[gunshots]
-[man grunting]
[man groans]
[grunts]
[squirting]
["Some Enchanted Evening" playing]
♪ Who can explain it? ♪
♪ Who can tell you why? ♪
♪ Fools give you reasons ♪
♪ Wise men never try... ♪
[gun firing]
[grunts]
[grunting]
[screaming]
[song continues playing]
♪ When you feel her call you ♪
♪ Whoa ♪
♪ Across a crowded room ♪
♪ Then fly to her side... ♪
Get that jelly mold out of here!
[grunting]
[song continues playing]
♪ Or all through your life ♪
♪ You may dream all alone ♪
♪ Some enchanted evening ♪
♪ You may see a stranger ♪
♪ Across a crowded room... ♪
[explosion]
[song continues playing]
♪ And somehow you know ♪
♪ You know even then... ♪
[screaming]
[song continues playing]
♪ That somewhere you'll see her... ♪
[yells]
[song continues playing]
♪ Again and again... ♪
[yelling]
Whoa. whoa. whoa. Easy. pal.
[grunts]
Sir. please don't make me use force.
-[hissing]
-[sniffing]
Oh. jeez.
[grunts]
-[grunts]
-[gasps]
[screaming]
[splattering]
[song continues playing]
♪ Some enchanted evening ♪
♪ When you find your true love... ♪
[yelps]
[beeping]
[timer beeping]
[Lucy panting]
[Moldaver] Welcome.
Oh.
I think I know who you are.
Everyone knows who I am.
But do they know who they are?
They are the product
of one of life's tricky little choices.
So. I'm gonna offer you a choice.
Them or her.
[Stephanie whimpers]
-[Lucy] Hey. Hey. hey. Stop.
-[Hank] Come on.
-Dad.
-Trust me. please.
-We have to-- No. no. stop!
-[door locks]
You are my world.
[grunting]
-Dad!
-[pounding on door]
Dad!
Stop! Stop it! Dad!
[pounds on door. yelps]
You look like your mother.
Where are you taking him?
To the real world.
You should see it sometime.
No. wait! Stop!
Stop! Stop!
Maybe you should do what you do best.
-Stop!
-Run and hide.
[beeping]
[Stephanie gasps]
[rapid beeping]
[breathing heavily]
[grunting]
["So Doggone Lonesome"
by Johnny Cash playing]
-[all shouting]
-Hit him again!
No. wait. wait. No. no.
...me kicking your ass.
You like that. huh?
[groaning]
Yo. let's go. Let's go.
[breathing heavily]
[Dane] Hey. Wow.
How's your nose?
[grunts]
I can still smell.
It's just mostly blood.
Flesh is weak. but Steel endures.
I... I know.
-Come on.
-Yeah.
[song continues playing]
♪ If they ask me.
I guess I'd be denying ♪
♪ That I've been unhappy all along ♪
♪ But if they hurt my heart
They'd hear it crying ♪
♪ "Where's my darling?
When's she coming home..." ♪
[Felix] It is the duty
of the Brotherhood of Steel
To secure the Wasteland.
One day. as squires.
you will help knights find
And identify pre-war tech.
Aspirant Maximus.
Can you identify this relic?
It's a... [clears throat]
...rotor.
[yelps]
[Felix] A circuit.
The ability to defend yourself
is but one part of your training.
We are the finders and the preservers.
[Maximus groans]
Unless you know
what to find and preserve.
You are more useful as a corpse.
[whirring]
Now. look at that shit.
[boy] What kind of model is that?
It's the T-60.
Imagine getting to put on
one of those every day.
[boy chuckles]
Wonder why they're here.
[officer over radio] A-17.
A-28.
B-11.
N-24.
[panting]
[flies buzzing]
-Come on. got something to show you.
-Latrine duty's a two-person job.
I said come on.
All this shit isn't going anywhere.
[panting]
[chuckles]
[Shortsight] Aspirant Dane?
-Uh... uh. this was my idea--
-You're being summoned. Come with me.
["All Over Again"
by Johnny Cash playing]
♪ Every time I look at you
I fall in love... ♪
[man whoops]
[song continues playing]
♪ All over again... ♪
[grunting]
[indistinct shouting. whooping]
[cheering]
What's going on?
A bunch of us have been chosen
to get anointed.
Hey. what's your title gonna be?
Squire. To Knight Titus.
And get this. we're going to the wilds.
-Hell yeah. you are!
-[Maximus] Yo. D!
[all chanting] D! D! D!
[indistinct chatter. laughter]
[grunting]
[yelling]
[screaming]
[laughter]
[Dane screaming]
[groans]
[groaning]
What happened?
[Dane groaning]
Give me that.
[screaming]
-[men grunting]
-[intense. ominous music playing]
[Maximus panting]
["Brighter Side"
by Connie Conway playing]
♪ There's a brighter side ♪
♪ To every dark. dark cloud ♪
♪ And there's a smiling face
In every crowd... ♪
[whimpering]
[panting]
[song continues playing] ♪ All your
troubles will soon fade away ♪
♪ There's a brighter ♪
♪ Brighter side ♪
[indistinct chatter]
[Reg] Everyone settle.
I have a proposal for the assembly.
[chatter dies down]
We send a search party
to the surface to find my dad.
-[murmuring]
-[man] Go to the surface?
We can spare four people
from farm duty for up to two weeks.
Even with our dwindled numbers.
Sorry. Lucy. but you're talking
about opening the outer Vault door?
Just for under a minute. okay?
-It's just enough time to--
-Okay. I know we're brainstorming here.
There's no bad ideas in a brainstorm.
-[man] Maybe a few.
-But that's not something
That we ever do
or have ever done. never ever. ever.
-I know. I know that. but--
-I know we're all hurting right now.
But our first priority has to be
to maintain the security of this Vault.
That means not opening any of our doors.
Well said. Betty.
[Woody] Yes. thank you. Betty.
Okay. let's move on.
-[Norm] They don't wanna find Dad.
-[sighs]
If they did. they wouldn't
get to be in charge.
[sighs]
[exhales]
-Hey. Davey.
-Hey.
How's your day going?
Bad as everyone else's.
[groans softly]
[muttering]
[static clicking]
[Lucy exhales]
Hold the elevator.
Take care of Norm till I'm back. okay?
I
can't.
I'm going with you.
-Chet--
-What you're doing is insane.
You don't even know which way to go.
It isn't like the Vault out there.
It's big.
Chet...
I'm not letting anyone else
get hurt on my behalf. okay?
Oh. Lucy.
Oh. okay. Here we go.
Shit.
I just tranq'd him.
I'll do the same to you
if you try to follow me.
I'm too chicken. but thanks.
[exhales]
I'm bringing him home.
[alarm blaring]
[whirring]
[hissing]
Stop! Lucy!
Are you mad?
Young lady. come back here right away!
[Reg] Lucy!
[breathing heavily]
Lucy. no!
That didn't work.
Okey dokey.
[exhales]
[gasps]
We have given you a name.
Food... education. a place in the world.
So...
We expect you to give us the truth.
Why did you join the Brotherhood?
To hurt the people who hurt me.
I understand
you're a friend of Aspirant Dane.
Yes.
You're aware of their injury?
-Yes.
-Do you know who did it?
No.
Your fellow aspirants say it was you.
[footsteps thudding]
No. I... [stammering] I... I wouldn't.
Why not?
Your friend was promoted. you were not.
You have ambitions. don't you?
[knight] Speak.
I... I didn't... I didn't do it.
I did not. I...
[hesitates] I wanted it to happen.
Is that wrong?
Yes.
[chuckles] Yes.
Violence...
It's merely a tool.
We use it to bring order
to the Wasteland.
But violence against a Brother of Steel
Is a sign of weakness.
Are you?
Weak?
I... I don't wanna be. I...
You have anything else to say
in your defense?
I just...
I... I wanna thank you.
[stammers] For your guidance
and for giving me a home.
I... I had no place in the world. so...
If I can help the Brotherhood
make it better...
Eden or whatever.
Even if it means
giving my own life... I'll do it.
And I'd be grateful to the Brotherhood
for giving my life meaning.
Good boy.
Then you will be
Knight Titus' new squire.
[breath trembling]
It's not so bad.
At least here
no one steals your rations.
They said I'll still have a place
at the Brotherhood.
I heard you got my spot.
You know who did it?
[Dane sighs]
Well. I've narrowed it down
to any one of those assholes.
[laughter]
-You like that? There you are.
-No! Stop it!
They asked if it was you.
Yeah. they asked me the same thing.
I told them you wouldn't hurt a fly.
[Felix] Aspirant Maximus.
It is your most sacred duty
to protect the Brotherhood.
After which it is your most sacred duty
to protect the mission.
To protect your lord. Knight Titus.
Do you accept?
[Quintus] Our mission comes
from the highest clerics
In the Commonwealth.
It is believed that a denizen
of the Enclave
Has escaped.
The Enclave's real?
And that he has with him
an object of profound potential
To harm our nation. or to save it.
Each knight in this legion...
Will search a section of the wilds
for this target.
Brothers...
We exist for moments such as these.
Go forth with honor!
And may the shape of the future
be cut by your sword!
[aspirants] Yeah!
Approximation of the target
for your lord.
You're dismissed. Aspirant.
[whirring]
[Maximus panting]
[indistinct radio transmission]
-[distant gun firing]
-[lively music playing]
[lively chatter]
-[loud gunfire]
-[groans]
[groaning]
[Slim] How do we know which grave?
[Honcho] Well. Slim.
we look through the fresh ones.
Don Pedro has our friend dug up
once a year. cuts his pieces off.
And puts him right back in the ground.
Bingo.
Shit.
You're telling me this supreme badass
we're looking for
Is a godforsaken mutant?
Have some respect.
That's your prospective co-worker
you's talking about.
And our ticket to a big pay-off.
Don. you said you knew this guy.
I said I knew of him.
My pop worked with him once.
Your pop? How long has this asshole
been moldering in the ground?
How do we know he's not feral?
That is why
-We brought our little friend.
-[chicken clucking]
A feral ghoul can't abide a chicken.
If he goes for him. we kill him.
[clucking]
[grunting]
[both groaning]
-Whoa. whoa.
-[panting]
[creaking]
[squeaking]
[breathing heavily]
[groaning]
[shudders]
[coughing]
[hawks]
[groaning]
-[cracking]
-[groaning]
[grunts]
-[cracking]
-[grunts]
[groaning softly]
Ah.
Well. well. well.
Well. is this an Amish production
of The Count of Monte Cristo.
Or just the weirdest circle jerk
I've ever been invited to?
[laughing]
Welcome back.
I'm Honcho.
-Now. you don't even know us.
-No.
-I do not.
-[chicken clucking]
Does that count?
Should I shoot him?
Would you shut the fuck up?
We. uh... we got a proposition for you.
A bounty came down.
Well. a huge one.
Enough to be a last score for me
and whoever's with me.
Yeah. Now. somebody made a run...
From the Enclave.
Well. what makes you think
I'd give a good goddamn about that?
It ain't where they's running from
I figured you'd be interested in.
It's where they's running to.
That witch Moldaver. in California.
That's where you from. ain't it?
Originally. I mean.
[vocalist yodeling]
Now. what the fuck would you know
about where I'm from?
Well. that don't sound like gratitude.
do it. boys?
How about we put you
right back in that hole
So Don Pedro can have his fun with you
for the next 30 years?
Well. I tell you what. boys.
Whenever somebody says
they doing one last job.
That usually means
your heart's not in it.
Probably never was.
Well. for me. well...
I do this shit for the love of the game.
[grunting]
[gasps]
[whimpering]
[Honcho panting]
You right. friend. about one thing.
This right here was your last job.
That paycheck wasn't quite
what you expected.
But. well. you know what they say.
Us cowpokes...
[grunts. yelps]
[thuds]
...we take it as it comes.
[chicken clucking]
["Crawl Out Through the Fallout"
by Sheldon Altman playing]
♪ Crawl out through the fallout. baby ♪
♪ When they drop that bomb ♪
♪ Crawl out through the fallout ♪
♪ With the greatest of aplomb ♪
♪ When your white count's
getting higher ♪
♪ Hurry. don't delay ♪
♪ I'll hold you close and kiss
Those radiation burns away ♪
♪ Crawl out through the fallout. baby ♪
♪ To my loving arms ♪
♪ Through the rain of strontium-90 ♪
♪ Think about your hero ♪
♪ When you're at ground zero ♪
♪ And crawl out through the fallout
Back to me ♪
♪ Why don't you crawl out
Through the fallout back to me? ♪
Through the fallout back to... ♪
♪ Me? ♪
[lighter flicks]
Oh.
Hello there.
Now. how about we turn on some lights?
[Wilzig] You need to go home.
Vault dwellers
are an endangered species here.
I'm not going back without my dad.
[Betty] You could have destroyed
the last vestiges of civilization.
[Dervin] What are you looking at?
[Norm] A murderer in a cage.
[Dervin] I don't know what the people
of Vault 32 were up to.
But it was anything but innocent.
[Lucy] What happened up here?
[Maximus] I think everybody
wants to save the world.
They just disagree on how.
[Lucy] I wonder if anyone survived.
[Roger] How long since
you first started Wastelanding?
A long time.
[snarls]
[Lucy] What are you?
[Ghoul] Oh. I'm you. sweetie.
Just give it a little time.
-[Mr. Handy] Welcome!
-What the fudge?
[Sebastian] Forget Hollywood.
You're a product. I'm a product.
The end of the world is a product.
[Charles] Vault-Tec is a trillion-dollar
company that owns half of everything.
[Cooper] I guess
everything's a conspiracy. right?
[Charles] Unless the people
do something about it.
[Ghoul] Ain't much stays clean
up here. Vaultie.
You'll see.
[roaring]
[screaming]
[Ghoul] You look out
at this wasteland...
looks like chaos.
But there's always somebody
behind the wheel.